Finding Aid for University Council (University of Michigan) records, 1931-1949, 1970-1989
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
University Council (University of Michigan) records 1931-1949 1970-1989
University of Michigan. University Council.
2.25 linear feet
87338 Bimu B31a 2
The University of Michigan's University Council was first conceived in 1931 as a representative government that would establish academic and university policies and serve in tangent with the University Senate and the Board of Regents. A second University Council was established in 1970 under bylaw 7.02 to create rules of conduct for the university. Both entities were eventually absorbed or disbanded. The primary holdings of these records include council's correspondence, committee reports, topical files, and meeting minutes with accompanying materials..
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Records received from several different sources (Donor numbers 234, 5662, 3572, and 8102 ). A small addition was gathered from the records of the Michigan Student Assembly (10, 243) in August 2009. Donor:
The collection is open to research.
In May 1931, the Board of Regents of the University of Michigan authorized the establishment of a University Council. Previous to 1931, the faculty government had used the town hall system of government. Under this system, named the University Senate, any faculty member that had achieved the rank of assistant professor or higher automatically became a sitting member. This resulted in a body with an unwieldy membership of upwards of 500 that met as few as four times a year. Attendance was also generally low unless a particularly interesting topic was announced. As the university grew, the senate recognized the need for effective and united communication and leadership.
The University Council, therefore, was conceived as a "federal organization" in the method of representative government. The first council consisted of: the university president, twenty-two exofficio members (including many deans, directors, and even the librarian and registrar), and thirty-four representatives elected, based on population size, from varying schools and colleges. The council replaced the former Senate Council (not to be confused with the University Senate) and took over the legislative arm of the University Senate, with the Senate maintaining oversight. Additionally, the University Senate's thirty committees were expected to annually report to the University Council.
The council was tasked with establishing university policies regarding, "a liberal and comprehensive policy of education; for the maximum utilization of the university; for the government, guidance, and discipline of the student body, and oversight of its activities...and to coordinate leadership and effectiveness of colleges and schools (September 1931 meeting). To accomplish this end, the council formed five standing committees: 1) Program and policy, 2) Educational policies, 3) Student relations, 4) Public relations, 5) Plant and equipment. In 1948, upon recommendation of the provost, the Regents approved a resolution which abolished the University Council. Most of its functions were taken over by a reconstituted and much more powerful Senate Advisory Committee on Academic Affairs (SACUA).
In February 1970, the University of Michigan Board of Regents established a new University Council to serve as a mechanism through which, according to the bylaw 7.02, "uniform regulations [could be developed] governing the conduct of... students, teaching staff,... and administrators... where such regulations (a) Promote the educational goals of the University, and (b) Are of common concern and apply generally to all of the above mentioned segments of the University community." Although the two University Councils carried out similar missions, there is no mention in the 1970s Regent's Proceedings that the second council was a direct descendent or reanimation of the 1931 University Council.
The 1970 University Council was composed of three students, three faculty, and three administrators/staff. Anything passed by the council would then need ratification by the Senate Assembly, Michigan Student Assembly (MSA), and the Regents. By 1987, the University Council was stalemated. According to the July 1988 University Record, the council had failed to pass one policy in its seven-year life due to its complicated structure for ratification. The Regents gave the council one year to develop workable amendments to the bylaw in order to make itself functioning and effective; otherwise, the sunset clause in the bylaw would disband the council in May 1989. The bylaw was extended until December 1989, however, the last mention of the council can be found in the December 1989 Regents Proceedings.
The University Council records include eight series: Standing Committees, Committees (reports), Correspondence and Other Papers, Correspondence with Board of Regents, Topical Files, Minutes (bound volumes), Accompanying Documents (bound volumes), and University Council, 1970-1989. The records primarily document the original University Council in operation from 1931 to 1948. Records from this period present a broad overview of campus issues and policies. The materials offer insight into how the university adapted to changes brought about during World War II.
Subjects:
University of Michigan--Administration.; University of Michigan. Senate.
- Standing Committees, 1931-1947
  The Standing Committees (.15 linear feet) series contains documents relating to the organization, amendments, decisions on policies and programs under the jurisdiction of the University Council's separate committees.
  - Educational Policies, 1931-1947 (Box 1)
  - Plant and Equipment, 1931-1943 (Box 1)
  - Program and Policy, 1931-1942 (Box 1)
  - Public Relations, 1931-1945 (Box 1)
  - Student Relations, 1931-1943 (Box 1)
- Committees (Reports), 1937-1941
  The Committees (Reports) (.25 linear feet) include progress and informative reports in various areas being monitored by the University Council, such as accredited schools, discipline, and intercollegiate athletics.
  - Alumni Relations, 1933-1934 (Box 1)
  - Accredited Schools, 1931 (Box 1)
  - Bureau of Appointments and Occupational Information, 1934-1944 (Box 1)
  - Calendar, 1937-1938 (Box 1)
  - Cooperation with Educational Institutions, 1932-1946 (Box 1)
  - Discipline, 1932-1934 (Box 1)
  - Extension Service, 1931-1940 (Box 1)
  - Foreign Students and International Center, 1931-1947 (Box 1)
  - Honorary Degrees, 1932-1939 (Box 1)
  - Honors Convocation, 1931-1946 (Box 1)
  - Intercollegiate Athletics, 1930-1944 (Box 1)
  - Latin American Relations, 1943 (Box 1)
  - Lectures, 1936-1941 (Box 1)
  - Library, 1933-1942 (Box 1)
  - Military Science and Tactics, 1932-1949 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous, 1937-1947 (Box 1)
  - Orientation Period, 1937-1947 (Box 1)
- Correspondence and Other Papers
  The Correspondence and Other Papers and Correspondence with Board of Regents (.10 linear feet) series contain letters and several communications involving the University Council.
  - 1931-1936 (Box 1)
  - 1937-1944 (Box 1)
- Correspondence with Board of Regents, 1931-1947
  - 1931-1947 (Box 1)
- Topical Files
  The Topical Files (.25 linear feet) cover a wide range of materials having to do with the agendas, formation, and management of the University Council itself. One file contains materials relating to Louis A. Hopkins, the University Council Secretary.
  - Hopkins, Louis A., 1931-1941 (Box 1)
  - Membership, 1931-1936 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous, 1931-1947 (Box 1)
  - Organization, 1931 (Box 1)
  - Programs and Agenda, 1931-1944 (Box 1)
  - Questionnaires, 1931-1932 (Box 1)
  - Three term plan, 1942 (Box 1)
- Minutes, 1931-1947 (bound volumes)
  The Minutes (bound volumes) (.25 linear feet) of the University Council contain the meeting minutes of the Council, and are complimented by the Accompanying Documents (bound volumes) (.5 linear feet) which have narratives and other materials relating to topics discussed at University Council meetings, arranged in chronological order.
  - 1931-1936 (Box 1)
  - 1937-1942 (Box 1)
  - November 9, 1942-May 26, 1947 (Box 1)
- Accompanying Documents, 1931-1945 (bound volumes)
  - 1931-1932 (Box 1)
  - 1932-1933 (Box 1)
  - 1933-1934 (Box 2)
  - 1934-1935 (Box 2)
  - 1935-1936 (Box 2)
  - 1936-1937 (Box 2)
  - 1937-1938 (Box 2)
  - 1938-1939 (Box 2)
  - 1939-1940 (Box 2)
  - 1940-1941 (Box 2)
  - 1941-1942 (Box 2)
  - 1942-1943 (Box 2)
  - 1943-1945 (Box 2)
- University Council, 1970-1989
  The University Council, 1970-1989 (.75 linear feet) series contains documents representing the later University Council activities. A significant portion of the series relates to the council's attempts to redefine bylaw 7.02 before its expiration. Correspondence with the Board of Regents and President Duderstadt are also present in the discussion to determine the future of the council. Other topics of interest include studies determining the need for campus police, firearm registration, noise on the Diag, and policy for protests on University property. Minutes in this series are partial at best.
  - Articles of Interest, June-September 1988 (Box 2)
  - Civil Liberties and Civil Liberties Board, April 1986-May 1989 (Box 2)
  - Croxton, Tom, February-April 1989 (Box 2)
  - Emergency Guidelines Drafts and Communications, 1970-1971 (Box 2)
  - Establishment of Campus Police, 1970-1974, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Firearm Regulations, 1970 (Box 2)
  - Freedom of Speech, May 1988-November 1989 (Box 2)
  - Formal Mechanisms, January-November 1989 (Box 2)
  - History, December 1988-June 1989 (Box 2)
  - Member Communication, undated, May 1988-September 1989 (Box 2)
  - Membership, 1970-1972 (Box 2)
  - Minutes, May 1970-February 1974, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Minutes, undated, February-December 1989 (Box 2)
  - Neutral Observer, undated, June 1988-March 1989 (Box 2)
  - Noise on the Diag, 1970 (Box 2)
  - Notes, undated, November 1988-May 1989 (Box 2)
  - Ordinance Governing Use of Arboretum, 1971 (Box 2)
  - Organization, 1970-1974 (Box 3)
  - Other Schools' Procedures, 1971-November 1988 (Box 3)
  - Racism, February 1989 (Box 3)
  - Regents Action July 1988-May 1989 (Box 3)
  - Regents Bylaws 2.01, 5.09, 7.02 October 1975-November 1988 (Box 3)
  - Report on Campus Police Protection, 1971-1972 (Box 3)
  - Rules of the University Community Drafts and Communication, 1970-1974 (Box 3)
  - University Council Rules and Procedures, March 1973-February 1989 (Box 3)